Hello!
In this episode, I’ll explain the structure
to the Web Content Accessibility Guidelines
— WCAG — and how you can start following
their requirements.
My name is Eric Eggert and I work in Web Accessibility
for over 10 years.
You can follow me as @yatil – Y - A - T - I - L – on social media.
Now, what is WCAG?
The Web Content Accessibility Guidelines are a set of principles, guidelines and
success criteria that lead you to accessible web content.
They are a web standard published by W3C,
the World Wide Web Consortium, and with every
web standard the assumption is that web content
creators adopt it into their practices.
Version 1 was published in 1999, so over 20
years ago, and Version 2 in 2008.
It was refreshed in 2018 with WCAG 2.1, which is the current version.
What’s the difference between WCAG versions,
you ask?
Version 2.0 was a complete rewrite with new
principles and a new structure.
It completely replaced WCAG 1.0 which was
technically not holding up anymore.
WCAG 2.0 is agnostic to technology, which gave
it a longer shelf-life out of the box.
And it is the basis for accessibility today.
2.1 expanded on WCAG 2.0 by adding new criteria
but without removing or changing any of the
existing 2.0 guidelines.
Think of 2.1 as an extension of WCAG 2.0.
WCAG 2.2, which is supposed to be coming out
soon, basically does the same thing with probably
one exception.
Subscribe to this channel and click the bell
icon to get notified about new videos, including
a WCAG 2.2 introduction once it is ready.
When I talk about WCAG in the future, you
can always assume WCAG 2 and I will say the
specific version number when that’s necessary.
That also means that if you conform to WCAG
2.1, you automatically conform to WCAG 2.0.
How neat!
More about conformance in a bit.
Let's talk about the structure of WCAG 2.
The main — normative — WCAG document has
three levels of guidance:
The first level is Principles.
Principles are basic qualities that every website needs to
have when it comes to accessibility.
2. Guidelines
Follow the guidelines when planning and designing
your website and application to make sure
you’re right on track.
3. Success Criteria
Verify your work by using success criteria
to see if you have been successful following
the guidelines and principles.
Sidebar: Normative information is information
that is the confirmed standard as published
by the W3C and not additional explaining information, which the W3C also publishes.
Let’s take a closer look at the Principles.
On the first level, four high-level principles
are defined, that you have to keep on your mind.
The first one is “Perceivable”.
Information and user interface components
must be presentable to users in ways they can perceive.
This principle makes sure that disabled people
can see the content or have alternatives available
in case they need them.
It covers making images perceivable through
alternative text and videos through captions
and audio descriptions.
2.Operable
User interface components and navigation must
be operable.
This principle allows users to use their preferred
technology to operate the website or web application,
for example many users can’t use a mouse,
either because they are using a screen reader
or a refreshable braille display to interact
with a website.
Others might have repetitive strain injury
(RSI) and just be temporally unable to use
a pointing device.
3. Understandable
Information and the operation of user interface
must be understandable.
This principle is a combination of making
sure that the content is easy to understand
and that you can interact with the website
or application in an understandable way.
For example, this principle covers specifying
the language of the page and parts of text
and also assisting users when filling out
forms.
4. Robust
Content must be robust enough that it can
be interpreted by a wide variety of user agents,
including assistive technologies.
This is probably the most technical principle.
It underlines how important good code is for
accessibility.
If your code is buggy or components are used
wrongly, the technology used by users might
not be able to interpret the information the
way you and users want them to.
Let’s take a look at the Guidelines.
The Guidelines are situated underneath the
principles and give more specific advice for
different situations.
Principle “1. Perceivable” has four guidelines:
1.1 Text Alternatives
Provide text alternatives for any non-text
content so that it can be changed into other
forms people need, such as large print, braille,
speech, symbols or simpler language.
Whenever content is on the page that is useful
or essential for the understanding of the
whole page or view, an alternative in text
form must be provided.
That alternative can be used in different
contexts.
1.2 Time-based Media
Provide alternatives for time-based media.
Time-based media is WCAG language for (mostly)
audios and videos.
Similar to “text alternatives”, this ensures
that people with different disabilities have
access to the media content.
For example, this guideline requires captions,
to enable access for people who cannot hear
narration, and audio descriptions, which enable
access for people who are unable to see a video.
1.3 Adaptable
Generate [!sic] content that can be presented in different
ways (for example simpler layout) without
losing information or structure.
This guideline prepares content to be used
out of the context or styled and viewed differently.
Here’s where semantic markup comes into
play.
It also means allowing users to use their
devices in any orientation.
1.4 Distinguishable
Make it easier for users to see and hear content
including separating foreground from background.
Avoid the use of color alone or low contrast
colors for text, information, and UI elements.
Allow resizing of text and changing the viewport,
for example by implementing a responsive design.
The second principle, Operable, has 5 guidelines:
2.1 Keyboard Accessible
Make all functionality available from a keyboard.
This is important as many technologies disabled
people use are using keyboard commands to
navigate around, even as the users are using
joysticks or other input methods.
2.2 Enough Time
Provide users enough time to read and use
content.
Avoid introducing arbitrary time limits and
let users take as much time as they need.
If there’s a requirement to restrict the
time for a certain task — for example for
security reasons — the user must be informed
and given a way to extend the timeout.
2.3 Seizures and Physical Reactions
Do not design content in a way that is known
to cause seizures or physical reactions.
This guideline targets flashing content and
motion animation.
Note that this guideline was extended to cover
physical reactions with WCAG 2.1, you might
find the old wording, which only talks about
seizures, occasionally.
2.4 Navigable
Provide ways to help users navigate, find
content, and determine where they are.
Examples of requirements that come from this
guideline are the ability to bypass blocks
of content on the page, having proper page titles, and
proper keyboard focus and a visible focus outline.
2.5 Input Modalities
Make it easier for users to operate functionality
through various inputs beyond keyboard.
New in WCAG 2.1, this guideline expands interaction
with the page or application when the keyboard
is not used.
For example, websites and applications must
provide an alternative to pinch and zoom gestures
you would use two fingers or pointers for.
Principle 3, Understandable has 3 guidelines:
The first one: 3.1 Readable
Make text content readable and understandable.
This guideline covers languages and language
transitions, the explanation of unknown words
and abbreviations, reading level, and pronunciation.
3.2 Predictable
Make Web pages appear and operate in predictable
ways.
The guidance in this guideline makes sure
that users are not surprised by the things
that happen on the website and also that common
elements look the same.
3.3 Input Assistance
Help users avoid and correct mistakes.
This guideline advises to label your form
fields in a useful way, identify errors and
provide suggestions on how to prevent errors
in the first place.
The last principle, Robust, has only one guideline:
4.1 Compatible
Maximize compatibility with current and future
user agents, including assistive technologies.
Write conforming HTML code, make sure that
the names, roles, and statuses of UI elements
are clear.
I won’t go into success criteria this time
— subscribe and click the bell to get a
notification when I do — but remember that
these build the ruleset to see if you have
met the minimum requirements of the guidelines.
You should always aim to exceed these success
criteria.
When you come across WCAG, you will quickly
stumble over techniques and understanding
documents.
They are linked right from the specification!
Note that those documents are non-normative
documents, they can help you to understand
WCAG but their guidance does not necessary
mean you meet WCAG.
The techniques are a collection of examples
of how to meet a success criterion, either
narrowly — WCAG calls this “sufficient
technique” — or as a best practice.
WCAG calls this an “advisory technique”.
Let’s talk about “Conformance” & “Conformance
Levels”
These phrases are often used when people talk
about web accessibility, especially in association
with WCAG and lawsuits.
Conformance determines that the website follows
all guidelines in WCAG and all applicable
success criteria are met.
It is usually used in the testing process
to have something “firm” or absolute to
test against.
However, there’s always some room for interpretation.
WCAG success criteria can have one of three
levels — A, Double-A and Triple-A — and to
reach that conformance non of your page can
violate any success criteria at that level.
The lowest level, A, ensures basic accessibility.
If you reach this level, you are not actively
excluding most disabled people.
The second level, Double-A, ensures accessibility
for most people with disabilities.
This is the level most laws and policies demand.
To reach it, you need to confirm to all success
criteria that are level A and Double-A.
The third level, Triple-A, are what I call
“stretch goals”.
These are either niche or otherwise hard to
achieve. But depending on your website it can
make a lot of sense to offer features that
fall into this conformance level.
So, that was an overview on the principles
and guidelines of WCAG as well as a look into conformance.
Stay tuned to learn more on different success
criteria and generally about web accessibility
on my channel.
Make sure to click subscribe and hit the bell
icon to not miss anything.
And of course you can support me on Patreon
at patreon.com/yatil or follow me at twitter.com/yatil.
That’s Y - A - T - I - L.
Thank you for watching.